Guide to the Edward N. Costikyan Papers
Rare Book and Manuscript Library Columbia University Libraries
Edward N. Costikyan Papers
1952-1985.
Costikyan, Edward N., 1924-
20.5 linear ft (ca.24,650 items in 47 boxes).
Columbia University. Rare Book and Manuscript Library, New York, NY.
MS#0287
4079678
This collection contains correspondence, memoranda, reports, documents, minutes, manuscripts and printed matter, 1952-1985, pertaining to Edward Nazar Costikyan, politician and lawyer.
Biographical Note
Edward Nazar Costikyan, politician and lawyer. Columbia University A.B., 1947; LL.B., 1949.
Scope and Content
Correspondence, memoranda, manuscripts, documents, and printed materials, almost entirely of a political nature and comprised largely of his leadership of the Democratic County Committee of New York, 1962-1964. Also included are files relating to a number of election campaigns in which he was involved, including those of Eugene McCarthy and Hubert Humphrey in 1968. The manuscript and related material for his book, Behind Closed Doors: Politics in the Public Interest. (New York, 1966), are also included. Among the major correspondents are Mario Cuomo, James A. Farley, Hubert H. Humphrey, Robert F. Kennedy, Herbert H. Lehman, Adam Clayton Powell, Adlai E. Stevenson, and Robert F. Wagner, Jr.
1979 Addition: Correspondence, memoranda, reports, documents, and minutes of the Temporary State Charter Revision Commission for the City of New York, 1972-1976.
1986 Addition: Political correspondence 1957-1981, nearly half of which includes materials relating to the 1977 New York City mayoral campaign of Edward I. Koch, and additional files on charter revision.
1993 Addition: Correspondence which chronicles the political activities of the New Democratic Club in the 1950s and 1960s.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged in seven series:
Series I: Catalogued Material
Series II: Uncataloged Correspondence
Series III: Personal and Political Papers
Series IV: 1979 Addition - Temporary State Charter Commission
Series V: 1980 Addition
Series VI: 1986 Addition - State Charter Revision, Koch Mayoral Campaign
Series VII: 1993 Addition - New Democratic Club, New York City Democratic Committee
Subjects
Democratic Party (N.Y.); Cuomo, Mario Matthew.; Farley, James A. (James Aloysius), 1888-1976.; Humphrey, Hubert H. (Hubert Horatio), 1911-1978.; Kennedy, Robert F., 1925-1968.; Koch, Ed, 1924-; Lehman, Herbert H. (Herbert Henry), 1878-1963.; McCarthy, Eugene J., 1916-2005.; Powell, Adam Clayton, 1908-1972.; Stevenson, Adlai E. (Adlai Ewing), 1900-1965.; Wagner, Robert F. (Robert Ferdinand), 1910-1991.; New York (N.Y.)--Politics and government.; Political campaigns.; Political participation.; Appointment books.; Financial records.; Invitations.; Minutes.; Photographs.; Press releases.; Prospectuses.; Reports.; Resumes.; Speeches.; Surveys.; Tape recordings.; Lawyers.; Politicians.
Acquisition
M-78-05-22 Costikyan, Edward N. Gift
Gift of Edward N. Costikyan, 1978, 1979, 1980, 1985, & 1986.
Access Restrictions
The following boxes are located off-site: Boxes 2-47. You will need to request this material from the Rare Book and Manuscript Library at least twenty-four (24) hours in advance to use the collection in the Rare Book and Manuscript Library reading room.
This collection has no restrictions.
- Series I: Catalogued Material
  Includes cataloged correspondence, manuscripts, and photographs.
  - Cataloged Correspondence
    - Beame, Abraham David (Box 1A-1B)
    - Berle, Adolph A. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Buckley, William F. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Cuomo, Mario (Box 1A-1B)
    - Duke, Angier Biddle (Box 1A-1B)
    - Farley, James A. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Finletter, Thomas K. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Harriman, W. Averell (Box 1A-1B)
    - Hogan, Frank S. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Humphrey, Hubert Horatio (Box 1A-1B)
    - Kelley, Walt (Box 1A-1B)
    - Kennedy, John Fitzgerald (Box 1A-1B)
    - Kennedy, Robert F. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Koch, Edward I. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Lefkowitz, Louis J. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Lehman, Herbert H. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Medina, Harold R. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Moynihan, Daniel Patrick (Box 1A-1B)
    - Muskie, Edmund S. (Box 1A-1B)
    - O'Dwyer, Paul (Box 1A-1B)
    - Powell, Adam Clayton (Box 1A-1B)
    - Rockefeller, Nelson Aldrich (Box 1A-1B)
    - Roosevelt, Eleanor Roosevelt (Mrs. Franklin D.) (Box 1A-1B)
    - Rosenman, Samuel I. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Stevenson, Adlai E. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Sutton, Percy E. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Wagner, Robert F., Jr. (Box 1A-1B)
    - Wirtz, W. Willard (Box 1A-1B)
  - Cataloged Manuscript: Lehman, Maxwell. The Koch Book. 1977 (1985 addition) (Box 1A-1B)
  - Catalogued Photograph: Hubert H. Humphrey (Box 1A-1B)
- Series II: Uncataloged Correspondence
  - 1955-1959 (Box 2)
  - 1960-1962 (Box 3)
  - 1962-1963 (Box 4)
  - 1963-1964 (Box 5)
  - 1965 (Sequence continues in Series V: 1980 Addition, Boxes 33-34) (Box 6)
- Series III: Personal and Political Papers
  - Personal
    - Invitations (Box 6)
    - Mailing lists (Box 6)
    - Millier, Irene B. (Box 6)
    - Press Releases and Statements (Box 6)
    - Richmond, Frederick W. (Box 6)
    - Speeches (Box 6)
    - Television and Radio (Box 6)
    - Youth Wants to Know (Box 6)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 6)
    - Behind Closed Doors: Politics in the Public Interest (New York, 1966). Manuscript and related material (Box 7)
    - Datebooks, 1962-1964 (Box 7)
  - Political
    - Campaigns (Box 8)
      - Abram (Box 8)
      - Beame (Box 8)
      - Humphrey (Box 8)
      - Johnson/Humphrey/R. Kennedy (Box 8)
      - McCarthy (Box 8)
      - Macchia (Box 8)
      - Schumacher (Box 9)
      - Silverman (Box 9)
      - Spiegel (Box 9)
      - Miscellaneous literature (Box 9)
    - Democratic Citizen's Committee, 1952-1953 (Box 9)
    - Democratic County Committee of New York
      - Correspondence (Box 9)
      - Committee for Democratic Voters (Box 9)
      - Dinners and Affairs (Box 9)
      - District Leaders' Communications (Box 9)
      - Election, 1964 (Box 9)
      - Fair Apportionment Campaign (Box 9)
      - Financial Statements (Box 9)
      - Madison Square Garden Rally, 1964 (Box 9)
      - New York Central Railroad (B. Kassal) (Box 9)
      - Proceedings, 1961-1963 (Box 9)
      - Public Relations (Box 9)
      - Reform Program (Box 10)
      - Rules and Regulations
        - Democratic Party (Box 10)
      - Miscellaneous (Box 10)
    - Memoranda (Box 10)
    - New Democratic Club (see also Box 41 A) (Box 10)
    - New York City- Opinion and Election Surveys, 1962-1963, 1965 (Box 10)
    - Patronage (Box 11)
      - New York County, 1962-1964 (Box 11)
      - Surrogates and attorneys lists; resumes; miscellaneous (Box 11)
    - Stevenson-for-President Club (Barbera) -1960 (Box 11)
    - Wright vs. Rockerfeller, 1962 (Box 11)
    - Miscellaneous, 1953-1961 and n.d. (Box 11)
  - Tape Recordings (3) (Box 12)
  - Photographs (Box 12)
  - Printed
    - Clippings (Box 12)
    - Miscellaneous (Box 12)
- Series IV: 1979 Addition - Temporary State Charter Commission
  - Temporary State Charter Commission for the City of New York, 1972-1975
    - Correspondences, 1972-1976 (3 Volumes) (Box 13)
    - Cases (Box 14)
    - Census (Box 14)
    - Charter Materials (Box 14)
    - Confidential (Box 14)
    - Costikyan
      - London Report (Box 14)
      - Remarks, 7/10/1974 (Box 14)
      - Speech, Decentralization... (Box 14)
      - Testimony (Box 14)
    - Diagrams (Box 14)
    - Drafts, (2 Folders) (Box 14)
    - Analysis of City Service (Box 15)
    - Bar Association Study (Box 15)
    - Drafts for Discussion (Box 16)
    - Drafts, Final, for Discussion (Box 16)
    - Exhibits (Box 16)
    - Gallup Poll (Box 16)
    - Haider Article (Box 16)
    - Hold (Box 16)
    - Hudson Institute (Box 16)
    - Implementation of Charter
      - Administrative Code (Box 16)
      - Correspondence (Box 17)
      - Charter Work Program (Box 17)
      - City Task Force Reports (Box 17)
      - Input from Outside Organizations (Box 17)
      - Internal memoranda (Box 17)
      - Enabling legislation, etc. (Box 17)
      - Community Boards (Box 17)
    - Interim Report, (2 Folders) (Box 17)
    - Issues for tentative decisions (Box 17)
    - Lehman memoranda (Box 17)
    - Lehman Press Release (Box 17)
    - Lehman Reports (Box 17)
    - Lindsay Administration (Box 18)
    - Lists (Box 18)
    - London (Box 18)
    - Memoranda
      - 1969-1974 (2 Volumes) (Box 18)
      - Duplicate (Box 18)
    - Minority Statements (Box 19)
    - Newsclippings (Box 19)
    - Outside Publications (Box 19)
    - Papers and letters, miscellaneous (Box 19)
    - Pencil Notes (Box 19)
    - Plan for Restructuring the Government of New York City (Box 19)
    - Progress Report (Box 19)
    - Proposals, etc., from other cities (Box 19)
    - Proposed legislation (Box 19)
    - Prospectuses (Box 19)
    - Publications (other agencies) (Box 19)
    - Publications, plans and reports (Box 20)
    - Resumes (Box 21)
    - Rockerfeller Press Conference (Box 21)
    - Sayre Report (Box 21)
    - Scott Commission Publications (Box 21)
    - Staff Working Papers (Box 21)
    - T.V. transcripts, speeches (Box 21)
    - Tentative Proposal Structure (Box 21)
    - Witnesses' Statements (Box 21)
    - Task force on Jurisdiction (Box 22)
      - Correspondence (2 Volumes) (Box 22)
      - General (Box 23)
      - Memoranda (Box 23)
      - Proposal - first draft (Box 23)
      - Prospectuses (Box 23)
      - Second drafts—Interim Report (Box 23)
      - Publications and reports (Box 24)
    - Minutes, Volume 1-16, 1972-1973 (Box 25-32)
- Series V: 1980 Addition
  - Correspondence
    - Personal, 1957 (Box 33)
    - re Behind Closed Doors. 1965-1967 (Box 33)
    - Political
      - 1966-1967 (Box 33)
      - 1968-1972 (Box 34)
  - How to Win Votes: the Politics of 1980. New York, Harcourt Brace Jovanovich, 1980. Manuscript and typescript. (Box 35)
  - Lecture Notes (primarily New School for Social Research) 1967,1970 1972 (Box 36)
  - Speeches, Political, 1970-1975 (Box 36)
  - Subject Files (Box 37)
    - Charter Revision, 1969 (Box 37)
    - Judicial Selection
      - Predergast Plan (Box 37)
      - Other plans and articles (Box 37)
    - Mayoralty (Box 37)
    - Municipal Bankruptcy (Box 37)
    - Muskie, Edmund - campaign (Box 37)
    - Search Committees (Box 37)
- Series VI: 1986 Addition - State Charter Revision, Koch Mayoral Campaign
  - Temporary State Charter Revision Committee for New York City
    - European trip (Box 38-39)
    - Reports (Box 38-39)
  - Political Correspondence 1957-1981 (Box 40)
  - 1977 New York City mayoral campaign of Edward I. Koch
    - Miscellaneous materials (Box 40)
    - Correspondence (Box 41)
    - Series VII: 1993 Addition - New Democratic Club, New York City Democratic Committee
      Contains mostly correspondence which chronicles the political activities of the New Democratic Club (NDC and the New York City Democratic Committee (NYCDC in the 1950s, 1960s and 1970s. Also contains NYCDC minute book and a number of pamphlets, flyers, mimeograph manuscripts, and photographs. The Correspondence of the NDC centers around issues of employment. The Correspondence and minute book of the NYCDC pertains to its membership, organizational structure and official incorporation. Cataloged correspondents include Senator John F. Kennedy and Mario Cuomo. Includes miscellaneous campaign literature. Arranged Chronologically, then alphabetically by topic.
      - New Democratic Club 1957-1985 (see also: Box 10) (Box 41A)
        - Current, 1957-1966 (Box 41A)
        - Historical, 1954-1985, (2 Folders) (Box 41A)
        - Various Years, 1956-1964 (Box 41A)
        - Campaign (Box 42)
          - 1952-1955 (Box 42)
          - 1956-1957 (Box 43)
          - 1958-1960 (Box 44)
          - 1961-1962 (Box 45)
        - Constitution, 1965 (Box 45)
        - Politics, John F. Kennedy, 1960 (Box 45)
        - Program Commitee, 1961-1962
          - Campaign
          - 1966, (2 Folders) (Box 46)
          - 1968 (Box 46)
        - Chairs, 1966 (Box 46)
        - Job Search, 1966-1967 (Box 46)
        - Leadership, 1966-1967 (Box 46)
        - Politics, 1968, (2 Folders) (Box 46)
        - Reform Leader's Caucus, 1967-1968 (Box 46)
        - Smog, 1967 (Box 46)
        - Benefit, 1969 (Box 47)
        - Newsletter, 1969 (Box 47)
        - Politics, 1969-1971 (Box 47)
        - State Commitee Campaign, 1970. (Box 47)
        - Welfare Island, 1970. (Box 47)
        - Women's Political Caucus, 1972-1974. (Box 47)
      - New York City Democratic Committee, 1970-1976
        - Certificate of Type, [1970] (Box 47)
        - Correspondence, 1970-1976 (Box 47)
        - Membership list, 1970-1971 (Box 47)
        - Memos, 1970-1974 (Box 47)
        - Minute Book, 1970 (Box 47)
        - Notice of meetings, 1970-1972 (Box 47)
        - Press Releases, 1970 (Box 47)
        - Dinner, 1971 (Box 47)
        - Progress Report, 1971 (Box 47)
        - Resumes, 1971 (Box 47)
        - Agenda, 1972 (Box 47)